Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Memorabilia 5141 MB
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Memorabilia
1867-1968
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen (BLF&E)
5141 MB
16 cubic feet
16 linear ft.
Memorabilia.
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Memorabilia including badges, name plates, push pins, pens, license plates, posters, plaques, buttons and other miscellaneous items
5923974
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 01, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen was founded on December 1, 1873, at Port Jervis, New York, to provide mutual support for railroad firemen. The Brotherhood initially emphasized insurance, but by the late nineteenth century had branched out into labor-management relations.
At the turn of the century, the organization changed its name to the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen (BLFE) after permitting engineers to join its ranks. In 1969, the union merged with the Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, and the Switchmen's Union of North America to form the United Transportation Union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5141: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Records 5141 G: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Graphics 5141 P: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Photographs 5147: Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers Records 5467: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Records 5475: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen General Chairman, Boston and Maine Railroad Records 5611: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Honorary Register of Disabled 5646: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records 5869: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Local 807 (Auburn, NY) Additional Records 6146 P: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen Photographs 6176: Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen Additional Records
Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen.; Boardman, F. B.; Columbus, Frank S.; Leach, Joshua; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen --Collectibles; Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen
5923974
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - badges, 1937-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Four "Visitor" badges from "Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen" conventions (33rd, 36th, 37th, 38th)
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges, 1908-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Badges - "B. of L.F. & E, St. Louis Convention"; "B. of L.F. and E., Houston, Texas Convention"; "B. of L.F. & E., St. Paul, Minn"; "Souvenir, 11th Biennial Convention, B of L.F. & E, Columbus, O"; "Asst. to E. & M., BrotherhoodGreat Seal of the
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges, 1912-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Badges - "BrotherhoodDenver, Co., 28th Convention"; "B of LF & E, State Joint, 5th Sunday Meeting Pottsville, Pa., March 31, 1912"; "Asst. to Ed. & Mgr., Twenty-Sixth Convention B. of L.F. & E., Washington, D.C."; "Columbus, Brotherhood32nd Conventi
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: push-pins, buttons, pin (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Push-pins - "B.L.F & E"; "B of LF & E"; "-- Years Continuous Membership, B of LF & E" [for 5, 10, 25, 30 years]; buttons - "Member, B of LF & E, Organized 1873"; "Meeting of Train Service Men of United States, Canada & Mexico, Worcester, Mass., April
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen name plate (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges, 1947-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Badges - bronze - "B of LF and E, Houston, Texas, 1968 Convention"; "B. of L.F. & E., St. Louis Convention, 1963"; "BrotherhoodSan Francisco, 1947, 35th Convention"; "36th Convention, Boston, Mass., 1953, B of LF & E"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Badges - All three are two sided one side is green/red/white, and one is black "In Memoriam". All have lettering "Erie Lodge No.543, B. of L.F. & E., Jersey City, N.J." One is for "President".
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Badges - All three are two sided one side is green/red/white, and one is black "In Memoriam". All have lettering "Erie Lodge No.543, B. of L.F. & E., Jersey City, N.J.". One for "Conductor", "Outside Guard", & "Warden".
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Badges - All three are two sided one side is green/red/white, and one is black "In Memoriam". All have lettering "Erie Lodge No.543, B. of L.F. & E., Jersey City, N.J." One for "Past President", "Chaplin", & "Fin. Secretary"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges, 1904-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Badges - 1)-"Denver" with flower on pin, pendant is shaped like an eagle on top of a round medal - "June 1916, Twenty-Seventh Convention, Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen & Enginemen, Grand Lodge Ladies Society of B. of L.F.E."; 2)- "AFL-CIO, 5th Bienni
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges, 1904-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Badges - 4)-"Houston" with star shaped pendant with a raised picture of a bull - "Brotherhood, 922"; 5)-"Brotherhood" with star pendant "Houston, Texas, 29th Convention, 1922"; 6)-"Detroit" with pendant "Brotherhood, 1925" with picture of a city coas
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: badges, 1904-1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Badges - 7)-"Brotherhood, 31st convention, 1928" with pendant- raised pictures of state of California, train, ship and skyscrapers.; 8)-"Denver, Colorado, 1916, Twenty-Seventh Convention" with pendant "Brotherhood"; 9)-This badge is very deteriorated
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: stamps (Box 3)
  One stamp is of the signature of "Frank S. Columbus" the other is "From F.B. Boardman, Chairman, New York State Legislative Board, B. of L.F. and E."
- Stamp with man's profile depicted on it (Box 3)
  Metal stamp on a wooden block, the stamp depicts a man's profile. [Frank S. Columbus?]
- Gavel - Frank S. Columbus, F. B. Boardman (Box 3)
  Wooden gavel used by both Frank S. Columbus and F.B. Boardman. See information sheet included with gavel. Gavel head is missing 1/4 of it, looks to be split off.
- Gavel - from Tenth Biennial convention, 1906 (Box 3)
  Gavel used to open the Tenth Biennial Convention of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen. Meeting was called to order by Brother John J. Hannahan, Grand Master at Nine O'Clock A.M., September 10, 1906 in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
- License plates (Box 3, Folder 1)
  License plate - White w/red lettering "Brotherhood of Locomotive Fireman and Enginemen" w/red locomotive engine in upper right corner.
- Letter and picture about the "W.T. Doty, Memorial" (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Letter about constructing the W.T. Doty Memorial, and a photo of the memorial when complete
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: pens, money clip, cuff links, tie tack, pendant (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Gold pens - "95th Anniversary, Brotherhood1873-1968"; "Brotherhood15401 Detroit Ave., Cleveland, Ohio 44107"; silver money clip with Brotherhood emblem; gold pendant - shaped like locomotive with "537" lettering; cuff links and tie tack - gold with
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: funeral cards, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Funeral card - "Funeral of past Grand Master and founder of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, Joshua A. Leach"; card with information and picture of the funeral.
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: ritual booklet, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  "Ritual of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: misc. convention and meeting information, 1885-1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Invitations - "Excursion, Boston Lodge, No. 57, B. of L.F., Dinner at Plymouth Beach Pavilion"; "Fourth Annual Ball of Frisco Lodge, No. 51"; convention booklets - "Brotherhoodand Ladies Society, Twenty-Fifth Southern Union Meeting"; "Southern Unio
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: menus, 1947-1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Menus - "Southern Railway System, Buffet Service"; "Capital City Dinner, Honoring Democratic Candidates"; "Annual Columbus Day Banquet"; "Capital District Dinner, New York State Democratic Committee"; "Capital Hill Club Capers of 1947"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: misc. souvenir invitations, cards, etc., 1887-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Railway passes - "Erie Railway, May, 1877"; invitations - "First Annual Ball"; "Second Annual Concert and Ball"; Tenth Annual Ball" "Brotherhood, Locomotive, Firemen, No. 216, W.A. Foster Lodge, Fitchburg, Mass"; membership cards - "This is to ce
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: schedule book for Firemen, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  "Northern Pacific Railway Company, Schedule for Firemen, Effective July 1st, 1911"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: union due notice, death announcement, 1884-1934 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Death announcement for Thomas E. Ryan, "Grand Lodge, Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen., Grand Dues Notice, 1884-1885"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: model booklet describing the working of a locomotive engine, 1902 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Instruction book - "Mitchell's Models and Easy Lessons in Locomotive Running"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: souvenir booklets, 1899-1925 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Souvenir booklets - "Twenty-Second Anniversary, 1899, Van Bergen Lodge, No. 62"; "35th Anniversary and the 11th Biennial Convention"; "Souvenir, B. of L.F. & E., Detroit, Mich. " & "Houston, Texas"; "Program Fiftieth Anniversary, B. of L.F. & E."
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.): Time book, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  "Time Book, Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, Founded May 8, 1863, Locomotive Engineers Mutual Life and Accident Insurance Association, Organized December 3, 1867"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen: poster and chart descriptions (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Two sheets of paper with descriptive information about two pieces of memorabilia that were discarded due to bad disintegration. One is a poster from B of LF & E World's War Honor Roll and the other is a description of a chart that is part of the B of LF &
- Sound Scriber discs [contents to be determined] (Box 5)
- Holy Bible, 1886 (Box 6)
  "Holy Bible, Presented to Bartholdi Lodge #309, from Atlantic Lodge #291" - title page - "The Self-Interpreting Holy Bible, Containing the Old and New Testaments"
- Wooden horse - this was found in box 11 of 6021/008 and moved here (Box 6, Folder 2)
  small wooden horse, red, with accent stenciling
- D.B. Robertson Safety Award (Box 7)
  Wooden award/trophy with lettered metal plates and topped with a replica of two train engines. Top plate - "The Brotherhood, Protection-Charity-Sobriety-Industry"; bottom plate - "Locomotive Fireman of the Year"; "1958-John T. Matthews"; "1959-Russel
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - Placque - [James M. Duffy], 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Wooden Placque with copper picture of 3 men and a woman, and a copper plate lettered "James M. Duffy, Locomotive Fireman of 1965, Mrs. James M. Duffy, U.S. Rep. Harley O. Staggers, James M. Duffy, Pres. H.E. Gilbert, Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - Placque - [Richard J. Hansel], 1961 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Wooden Placque with copper picture of 3 men and a child, and a copper plate lettered "Richard J. Hansel, Locomotive Fireman of 1961, H.E. Gilbert, Pres. BLF &E, George Meany, Pres. AFL-CIO, Richard J. Hansel, John Keane, Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - Placque - [William R. Bennett], 1962 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Wooden Placque with copper picture of 4 men and a child, and a copper plate lettered "William R. Bennett, Locomotive Fireman of 1962, Frank Clement, Gov. Tennessee, William R. Bennett, H.E. Gilbert, Pres. BLF&E, Mark Erickson, U.S. Rep. Arnold Olsen, Brot
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - Placque - [Ralph M. La Rue], 1963 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Wooden Placque with copper picture of 3 men and a woman, and a copper plate lettered "Ralph M. La Rue, Locomotive Fireman of 1963, U.S. Senator Eugene McCarthy, Ralph M. La Rue, Mrs. R. La Rue, Pres. H.E. Gilbert, Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Eng
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - Placque - [Safety Award] (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Wooden Placque with gold plate and lettering - "Safety Award"; "Locomotive Fireman of the Month"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 1)
  Buttons - gold and blue with gold lettering "B of L.E. & E., L-S" with "FC" in the center
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 2)
  Buttons - gold, red, white, blue with gold lettering - "L.S., B of L F & E"; "25 Years Continuous Membership"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 3)
  Buttons (2 kinds) - 9 are silver with black lettering "40 Years"; "Ladies Society to the B. of L.F. & E." - 9 are gold with red and black lettering "40 years"; "Ladies Society to the B. of L.F. & E."
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 4)
  Buttons - silver, red, white, blue with gold lettering - "L.S., B of L F & E"; "25 Years Accumulated Membership"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 5)
  Buttons - gold and blue with gold lettering "B of L.E. & E., L-S" with "FC" in the center, with a 'banner' of gold attached to the top of button that says "Past President"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 6)
  Buttons - gold and blue with gold lettering - "50 Years"; Ladies Society to the B. of L.E. & E."
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - buttons/pins (Box 9, Folder 7)
  Buttons-triangular in shape, red, white, blue with gold lettering - "10 Years Continuous Membership"; L.S. B. of L. F&E"
- Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen - medal, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  Silver medal with "Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, 1925" in raised lettering
- Sound Scriber (record and playback) (Box 10)
  - Sound Scriber (record and playback) (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Sound Scriber (playback only) (Box 11)
  - Sound Scriber (playback only) (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Large bronze plaque honoring Joshua Leach (Box 12)
  - Large bronze plaque honoring Joshua Leach (Box 12, Folder 1)
    snapshot available
- snapshot available (Box 12)
- Large wood plaque Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen (emblem) (Box 13)
  - Large wood plaque - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen (Box 13, Folder 1)
- snapshot available (Box 13)
- snapshot available (Box 14)
- Large bronze plaque - Brotherhood of Locomotive Friemen..Building Fund Donors (Box 14)
  - Large bronze plaque - Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen, Grand Lodge HeadquartersBuilding Fund Donors, Groups & Organizations, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Large metal plaque (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Wood and bronze plaque -- honoring Frank S. Columbus (Box 15)
  - Large wood and bronze plaque: honoring Frank S. Columbus - 1885-1972 (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Images digitized from the collection. (Box 16)